Ada Lovelace was a brilliant woman that helped to develop the basis of all modern computing.
She had studied mathematics and was included in the scientific circles of the 19th century.
In special, she had contact with the work of Babbage and became fascinated by his machine.
At a certain point Ada asked Babbage to be her tutor, but he declined it.
However, Babbage recommended other great figure, Augustus DeMorgan.
DeMorgan accepted to advise her, and influenced her with his theories about logical relations and properties.
DeMorgan taught her some formalism and opened her mind to other points of view.
Based on that, Ada wrote her Notes about the Babbage Analytics Engine, and these Notes were published in 1843.
In this work she described the main logical structures still used nowadays in computers programming.
Few years later George Boole created his binary algebra system.
In 1937, Turing published a work describing his universal computer
and Claude Shannon described how circuits of switches can perform Boolean tasks.
At this point all theory was developed and the scientists were ready to design the first computers.